<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>God the believer's best stronghold in the worst times. A sermon preached upon the preservation of His Majesty's person, and the discovery of the late plot of the intended invasion. / By Edmund Godwin ...</title>
            <author>Godwin, Edmund.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1696</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 70 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 29 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A86068</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G967A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R177501</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">45789328</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 45789328</idno>
            <idno type="VID">172638</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A86068)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 172638)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English Books, 1641-1700 ; 2642:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>God the believer's best stronghold in the worst times. A sermon preached upon the preservation of His Majesty's person, and the discovery of the late plot of the intended invasion. / By Edmund Godwin ...</title>
                  <author>Godwin, Edmund.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 47 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Jonathan Robinson at the Golden Lion in St. Paul's Church-yard,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1696.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in: Lambeth Palace Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Nahum I, 7 --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-08</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:172638:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>God the Believer's beſt Strong-hold
in the worſt Times.</p>
            <p>A
SERMON
PREACHED
Upon the Preſervation of
His MAJESTY'S Perſon,
AND THE
Diſcovery of the late Plot of
the Intended Invaſion.</p>
            <p>By <hi>EDM<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ND GODWIN,</hi>
Rector of <hi>Cowley.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>Deo confiſi nunquam confuſi.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi>
Printed for <hi>Jonathan Robinſon</hi> at the Golden
Lion in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. 1696.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:172638:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:172638:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Worſhipful
Sir JONATHAN KEATE,
Knight and Baronet.</head>
            <p>WHereas formerly there
hath been ſome pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe
of my coming
into your parts to preach, and to
pay my Reſpects to your Worſhip
for Kindneſſes of old; when you,
and others with you, did largely
declare your Deſire of having me
your Miniſter at <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Walden:</hi>
I ſhould readily have accepted of
your Kindneſſes, but that the Vica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ridge-Houſe
was ſo ruinous, and a
Promiſe being paſt of my being elſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>where;
<gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:172638:3"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:172638:3"/>
               <pb facs="tcp:172638:4"/>
yet I muſt needs confeſs my
ſelf to be indebted ſince to come, and
give you a Sermon: So that I am
ſo long indebted upon that account,
<hi>Uſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> dum uſura ſuperat ſortem;
That the very Intereſt doth
far exceed the Principal.</hi> How<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever,
I would have you know, that
I ſtill bear an honeſt Mind, having
a Deſire to pay according to my A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility;
and though I cannot come
and pay what I owe in Perſon, yet
I have ſent my Subſtitute, this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
Meſſenger to ſupply my Place;
and knowing how well you, and
thoſe about you, ſtand affected to the
Preſent Government, I have pitcht
upon Printing a <hi>Thankſgiving-Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon</hi>
for the <hi>Diſcovery and Diſap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment
of the late Dangerous
Plot of Aſſaſſinating His Majeſty,
<pb facs="tcp:172638:4"/>
and the Invading this Kingdom
with a deſign of rooting out our
Religion,</hi> under the notion <hi>of the
Northern Hereſie:</hi> And I know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
how ſtedfaſt you have been, and
others about you, to the Truth, and
how ready you are to aſſiſt its Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourers,
and to reſiſt its Oppoſers,
I thought good to preſent you with
a taſte of what I did deliver upon
that Occaſion, hoping it may fall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
the Hands of ſome of that worthy
Family of the <hi>Hales,</hi> that former<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
were my Noble Benefactors. I
hope there are ſome of that Race a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>live
in thoſe Parts, though I hear,
to my Grief, that Worthy Lady, the
Lady <hi>Auſtin,</hi> is dead. God hath
hitherto prolonged my Life, and it
is much upon my Spirit to give you
a Viſit in thoſe Parts before I die.
<pb facs="tcp:172638:5"/>
I do but preſent you with a taſte of
my Labours, and wiſh they may be
well reliſht and received by you;
it then may be an Inducement to put
out more of my Labours, yet before
I die. I remember a Paſſage of
Biſhop <hi>Latimer</hi>'s, that he Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
in a Sermon before the King,
<hi>of one that had brought up his
Son at the Univerſity, and a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman
not far off from him, hav<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
a Living in his Gift newly fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len;
that he might gain it for his
Son, preſents him with a Diſh of
ten very fair Apples, and had put
into every one of the Apples 10
twenty Shilling Pieces, and ſent
his Man with them to the Patron,
and withal to deſire him to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
his Son to the Living of his
that was fallen.</hi> The Man having
<pb facs="tcp:172638:5"/>
delivered them, and deſiring him in
his Maſter's Name to remember his
Son for the Living; the Gentleman
ſeemed to be angry, <hi>and bid him
carry back his Maſter's Apples, he
would have none of them.</hi> Which
the Man did, and told his Maſter
that he would have none of his Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples.
Says his Maſter to him, <hi>Car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
them again, and deſire him but
to taſte one of them, and as he
likes that, to accept of the reſt.</hi>
Which the Man did, and tells him,
<hi>That his Maſter however did de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire
him but to taſte one of them.</hi>
Which he did, and finding 10 twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
Shilling Pieces in it, crys out,
<hi>I marry, if they be all like this,
thy Maſter's Son ſhall have the
Living. I will aſſure you,</hi> ſays
the Man, <hi>they all came off of the
<pb facs="tcp:172638:6"/>
ſame Tree:</hi> Though Symony was
in uſe then, yet not ſo openly practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced
as now a-days. The <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe that I
ſhall make of the Story, is only to
tempt you to a taſte of my Labours
in Print, and as this is reliſht it is
poſſible the World may have more of
them. So beſeeching the Lord to
bleſs you, and the Worthy Families
not far off from you, I muſt needs
acknowledge that I ſtill remain,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your very much obliged,
To ſerve You,
<hi>Edmund Godwin.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:172638:6"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Nahum I. ver. 7.</bibl>
               <q>The Lord is good, a ſtrong hold in
the day of trouble, and he know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
them that truſt in him.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> hath foretold
how in the latter perillous times,
<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, hard times for Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons
to keep Faith and a good
Conſcience; and indeed dangerous in which
to live, in regard of the abounding of Sin;
and we ſeem to be fallen into the ſame times
that the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> himſelf was fallen into,
mentioned <hi>2 Cor.</hi> 11. 26. as you may ſee
there: He was in Journeying often as His
Majeſty K. <hi>William</hi> hath been, in Perils of
Waters, in Perils of Robbers, in Perils by his
own Country-men, in Perils by other Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try-men,
in Perils in the City, in Perils in
the Country, in Perils amongſt falſe Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren,
and in Perils amongſt pretended
Friends; ſo that there hath been threatned
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:172638:7"/>
               <hi>ubique naufragium.</hi> However, God hath
been good, may his Majeſty now ſay, and a
Strong-hold, and a ſure Defence in all ſorts
of Troubles, and wonderfully delivered in
every Danger; hitherto he hath been an
<hi>Ebenezer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the foregoing part of the Chapter, you
have firſt the Inſcription of the Propheſy in
the firſt Verſe, and then a Deſcription of the
Almighty, firſt in his Power and Greatneſs
in five of the foregoing Verſes, and then in
Goodneſs and Mercy; having to deal with
many and mighty Adverſaries, as with <hi>Ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neveh</hi>
that great City, the Men whereof
were great Sinners before the Lord, and
had repented of their former Repentings in
<hi>Jonah</hi>'s time, and had returned with the
Dog to their former Vomit, and with the
Sow to their wallowing again in the Mire
of Sin, ſo <hi>that their latter State was now worſe
than the former;</hi> for which God threatens
them with the greateſt Plagues, and heavieſt
Judgments: But God is never ſo angry, but
in Wrath he can and will ſhew Mercy, and
knows his Friends from his Foes, according
to the Tenor of the Words of the Text,
<hi>The Lord is good.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So that the Words are like a Light ſhine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
in a dark place, or as a Haven or Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour
in time of a Storm, or a ſtrong Fort
or Tower in the day of Diſtreſs, to which
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:172638:7"/>
the Righteous may run and reſort in the
time of Danger, and be ſure to be ſafe. So
that you have in the Words,</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>Something affirmed,</hi> That the Lord
is good.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> You have the ſame confirmed
by a twofold Argument; As,</p>
            <p>1ſt. <hi>In that he</hi> is a ſtrong hold in the day of
trouble.</p>
            <p>2dly. <hi>In that he</hi> knows thoſe that truſt in him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>That God is good,</hi> is ſuch a Truth as we all
have cauſe to ſet our Seals unto, for he hath
not left himſelf without witneſs of doing of
us good, eſpecially of late in defending and
delivering of us; and ſo I ſhall come to take
notice firſt of the Time when it is that his
Goodneſs doth moſt appear, and that is in
the Time of Trouble; and then to whom
it doth appear, and that is to ſuch as know
him, or rather are known of him, ſuch as not
barely know him, but truſt in him.</p>
            <p>Now the Doctrines that I ſhall lay down
from the Words, are theſe;</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> 1. That God's People here in this
World meet with days of Trouble.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> 2. That they never find times ſo bad,
but ſtill they find God to be good.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:172638:8"/>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> 3. That in times of Danger, God
then more eſpecially will be a ſtrong
hold too.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Doct.</hi> 4. God knows ſuch as truſt in him
in a more ſpecial manner to ſave.</p>
            <p>On the firſt, namely, That God's People
here in this World, meet with days of
Trouble.</p>
            <p>Now we may take notice of this in all
the faithful Servants of God: God had one
Son without Sin, but he never had any
without Sorrow; his own Son that was the
head of the Church, was a Man of Sorrows;
and the firſt Man that died, he died for Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,
and ſo the Father of the Faithful,
who ever had greater or hotter Trials?
And ſo <hi>Jacob,</hi> in whoſe Poſterity the Church
was ſettled, How doth he complain that
<hi>few and evil were the days of his Pilgrimage;</hi>
yet they were full of Trouble, and the time
of Trouble is called <hi>the day of</hi> Jacob<hi>'s Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble;</hi>
and ſo <hi>Job,</hi> Who more troubled and
afflicted than he? And ſo <hi>David,</hi> that <hi>was
a Man after God's own Heart,</hi> yet how doth
he cry out? <hi>Lord, Remember</hi> David, <hi>and all
his Troubles,</hi> Pſal. 132. 1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> But how comes it about that ſuch
as are ſo Godly, are ſo ſorely afflicted?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:172638:8"/>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> Firſt, This comes from God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf.
<hi>2dly,</hi> From Satan, the God of this
World. <hi>3dly,</hi> From Satan's Inſtruments,
the Men of the World. Laſtly, From them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves,
or their near Relations.</p>
            <p>Firſt, This comes from God himſelf:
For Afflictions riſe not out of the Duſt, but
God ſends them, firſt to puniſh Sin paſt.
<hi>2dly,</hi> To purge Sin preſent. <hi>3dly,</hi> To pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent
Sin for the time to come.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to puniſh Sin paſt: I know indeed
that the Antinomians will not allow of ſuch
an Expreſſion to be uſed in reſpect of God's
own People and Children: They ſay God
only puniſhes from Sin, and not for Sin in
them: But doubtleſs we may ſpeak as the
Word of God ſpeaks without offence; now
ſays the Church, <hi>Lam. 3. 39. Wherefore doth
the living Man complain, is it not for the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment
of his Sin:</hi> And ſo <hi>Amos 3. 2. You
only have I known of all the Families of the
Earth; therefore I will puniſh you for all your
Iniquities.</hi> One would have thought it ſhould
rather have run thus, <hi>You only have I known
of all the Families upon earth, therefore I will
ſpare you for your Iniquities:</hi> No, but there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
I will puniſh you for your Iniquities;
you of all others ſhall be ſure to ſmart ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt
and ſoreſt here in this World. I confeſs
that in a ſtrict Senſe they cannot ſo proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
be called Puniſhments as Chaſtiſements,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:172638:9"/>
becauſe Chriſt hath born the Puniſhments
of Believers Sins in his own Body upon the
Tree, and when his Soul likewiſe was made
a Sacrifice to ſatisfy the Juſtice of God for
their Sin.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly,</hi> God ſends Afflictions on his own
People to purge Sin preſent: There are the
Remnants of Sin and Corruption in the
beſt of God's Children and Princes. Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
if they be ſick, they muſt be Phyſickt
as well as others: <hi>By this therefore,</hi> as it is
<hi>Iſa. 27. 9. ſhall the Iniquity of</hi> Jacob <hi>be purged;</hi>
and now there is a great difference between
Phyſitians purging, and God's purging of
his People and Children: When Phyſitians
purge their Patients, they many times purge
out the good Humours as well as the bad;
but God when he purges his Children, he
only purges out the bad Humours, as in the
place we named before; and this is all the
fruit, to take away his Sin; not to take the
Sinner, but to take away his Sin.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly,</hi> God ſends Troubles and Afflictions
on his own People and Children to prevent
Sin in them for the time to come, and to
keep them within compaſs: You know
what <hi>David</hi> ſaid of himſelf, <hi>Pſal. 119. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
I was afflicted I went wrong, but now have
I kept thy word, and kept in the right way:</hi>
And therefore God threatens his Apoſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal
Church, <hi>Hoſea 2. 6. Therefore, behold, I
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:172638:9"/>
will hedge up thy way with Thornes.</hi> She was
apt to break out into the Paſtures of forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den
Pleaſures; therefore God would ſet
Thornes in her paths, if ſhe would break
over, ſhe ſhould prick and wound her ſelf;
and if that would not do, God would make
a Wall that ſhe ſhall not find her paths;
Hedges may be eaſily troden down, but
Walls are not ſo eaſily climbed over. Thus
God threatens to do to his, when he intends
to do them good; and Afflictions are not ſo
properly ſaid to be threatned, as promiſed
to God's own People and Children, as you
may ſee <hi>Pſal.</hi> 89 30, 31, 32. therefore it is
added the <hi>33d</hi> Verſe, <hi>Neither will I ſuffer my
Faithfulneſs to fail;</hi> that is, in regard of ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>filling
what before he had promiſed.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>4thly,</hi> Again, God orders it ſo that they
ſhall have their days of Trouble here, that
they may not ſet up their reſt in this World,
as the other two Tribes and an half did on
this ſide <hi>Jordan,</hi> as People are too apt to do
when all things go well with them, and are
apt to flow in upon them; then they are
ready to talk of building Tabernacles here,
and never think of going hence: But now
that God may knock off their fingers from
things below, and make them know that
this is not their Reſt, God lets them meet
with many Calamities and ſore Troubles,
that ſo they may know that this is not their
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:172638:10"/>
Reſt, as God ſays to his own People, <hi>Mich.
2. 10. Ariſe, and depart, this is not your Reſt,
it is polluted;</hi> it is defiled with Sin, and can
give you no more Reſt than a Bed of
Thorns can do to a ſick Perſon. O! it is
polluted, and therefore it muſt not be your
Reſt. Sin hath polluted all things here in
this World, therefore get you hence; tho'
they ſhould combine altogether to do you
good, yet they cannot give you perfect
Reſt: When God made all things at firſt,
he made them very good, and there was that
in them then that might give Satisfaction to
the Heart of Man; but now Sin hath pol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luted
the Creature, and filled it with no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
but Dirt and Filthineſs. Sin hath not
only put our Mouths out of taſte that we
can take no Contentment, or find any Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfaction
in the Creature, but it hath emp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tied
it of all that was truly good in it: So
that now we have <hi>Carbones pro Theſauro,</hi>
Coals inſtead of golden Mines; ſo that God
doth this.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>5thly,</hi> That they may be weaned from
the World, and from all wordly things;
<hi>For the World paſſeth away, [1 Joh. 2. 17.]</hi>
and we muſt paſs away that are in it; for
we have here no abiding City, but yet the
People of God are too apt to let out their
Hearts and Affections on the things of this
preſent World: If they have all ſorts of
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:172638:10"/>
Flowers in their Garden, they are too apt to
make a Noſe-gay of them, and to hold them
ſo faſt till they wither in their hand: when
a full cup of Proſperity is fill'd out to them,
God many times anoints the brim with A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loes,
or ſome bitter thing, that they may not
drink too long of it, nor too much: Some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times
God beats their Plow-ſhares into
Swords, and turns their Rods into a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent.</p>
            <p>Again, God brings them into days of
Trouble for the trial of their Graces, both
for the trial,</p>
            <p>Firſt, Of the Truth of them.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Of the Strength of them.</p>
            <p>Firſt, The Truth of them; hang heavy
Weights upon rotten Boughs, and they break
them; but upon green and ſound Boughs,
and they bear them; unſound fruit will
hang upon the Tree in a ſtill and calm day,
but if it be ſtormy then down it falls. The
building upon the Sand may make as fair a
ſhew in a Sun-ſhine day, as that built upon
the Rock; but when the Floods come, and
the Winds blow hard, then down it falls,
when the other ſtands. An unſound Foot
may travel pretty well in ſoft and green
Way, but when it comes upon the hard
Stones, then it will be apt to boggle and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:172638:11"/>
halt. It was the Sword that did diſcover to
whom of right the Child did belong unto,
<hi>1 Kings</hi> 3. 24. There be many that think
their Graces are ſound and good, but when
a Storm, or any Hardſhip comes, how full
of Unbelief and Impatience, are they
there. That God may try his People's
Graces, whether they are ſound or no, he
brings many ſtormy days over their heads;
if Afflictions bring us nearer to God, it is a
great ſign they are ſanctified to us; but if
they drive us further from God, it is a great
ſign that they are in Wrath, and not for our
good. God ſpeaks to a Believer when he
afflicts him, as <hi>Iſaac</hi> did to <hi>Jacob</hi> when he
came to him for the Bleſſing; <hi>Come near me,
my Son, that I may feel thee whether thou beeſt
my very Son</hi> Eſau <hi>or no?</hi> So if they bring us
nearer to God, and we endure them with
patient ſubmitting to the Will of God with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out
any muttering or repining, it is a great
ſign that we are indeed the Children of
God.</p>
            <p>Secondly, He doth it alſo to try the
Strength of their Graces: It muſt be a
ſtrong Wing that muſt fly againſt the Wind,
weak Grace will hardly bear up in a ſtrong
day; <hi>If thou faint in the day of adverſity, thy
Strength is ſmall,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon, Prov.</hi> 24. 10.
To love God when he hears our Prayers,
and anſwers our Prayers preſently, is no
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:172638:11"/>
great matter; but to continue praying, when
he ſhuts out our Prayer, as he did the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,
<hi>Lam<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> 3. 8. and appears as an Enemy,
this argues ſtrength of Faith: It is an eaſy
thing to love God when he ſmiles upon you
with his Favours and Bleſſings; but to love
him when he hath a Frown in his Brow,
and a Rod in his Hand, this argueth
ſtrength: That fire of Love burns hot, that
many waters of Affliction cannot quench,
or put it out. We read in <hi>Matth.</hi> 15. of a
Woman that came to Chriſt with Words
in her Mouth and Sorrow in her Heart, and
all to move him to pity. At firſt he gave her
no anſwer; afterwards his Diſciples are her
Spokes-men in her behalf: After that Chriſt
calls her Dog, yet ſhe will not give him o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver;
a Cure ſhe came for, for her Daughter,
and a Cure ſhe muſt have afore ſhe goes
away. She doth in a manner confeſs her
ſelf a Dog, and doth but deſire the Favour
that Dogs are apt to have at their Maſter's
hands; a crum of his Charity. <hi>O Woman,</hi>
ſays Chriſt, <hi>great is thy Faith!</hi> O! it is
Strength of Faith that will truſt and reſt in
Chriſt when he doth not anſwer, nay when
he doth refuſe and reject, and ſeem to caſt off.</p>
            <p>Again, the Children of God have their
days of Trouble: That by this means God
might humble them, and bring down the
Pride of their Spirits, Pride and Ambition;
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:172638:12"/>
it is an ill Weed, and will not only grow in
the vaſt howling Wilderneſs, but often it
ſprings up in the Garden of God: Not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
wicked Men are guilty of this Sin, but
ſometimes the Children of God are apt to
be puft up with Pride, as we ſee it in <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah;</hi>
nay they are apt to be puft up with
their very Graces, as the Devil was with his
Excellencies; and whereas their Graces
ſhould be a means to keep them humble,
they will be apt to grow proud of them, if
they take not heed now to let out this blad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der
of Pride. Sometimes there is ſent a
Thorne in the Fleſh, as there was to <hi>Paul;</hi>
and ſometimes God thruſts in the Sword of
Affliction to let out the Corruption of this
big-bellied <hi>Vicu:</hi> A Sword was ſent to pierce
the Heart of the Bleſſed Virgin, that was
ſo highly exalted, in all probabilty to keep
her humble. It is the Speech of <hi>Elihu,
Job 33. 17. He chaſteneth Man with pain,</hi>
that he may hide Pride from Man: In the
<hi>14th</hi> Verſe, <hi>God ſpeaketh once, yea twice.</hi> God
ſpeaketh once by his Word, and again by
his Sword; once by his Word, and Man
heareth it not; and he ſpeaks again by his
Rod, and all to hide Pride from Man, and
that they may not think poorly of others in
regard of themſelves.</p>
            <p>Again, they meet with days of Trouble
that they may be made conformable to Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:172638:12"/>
Chriſt, God's dearly beloved Son, ſo
<hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 29. They are the Apoſtle's words
there; That Chriſt and his Members may
be all of a piece: The Children of God are
not made choice of, and appointed unto
Glory only, but they are alſo appointed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
Conformity to Jeſus Chriſt: You know
that whilſt he was God, he was in Glory;
but when he became the Son of Man, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>came
a Man of Sorrows, and we hid our
faces from him, as it is <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53. as if we were
aſhamed of him. Trouble was as a Thred
drawn thorow the whole courſe of his Life:
Now that God's Children may be confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable
to Chriſt, they meet with days of
Trouble; they muſt be afflicted and miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uſed;
for if they have done ſo to the green
Tree, what will they not do to the dry, who
is no better than fit Fuel to the everlaſting
Fire?</p>
            <p>Again, they meet with days of Trouble,
that they may be the more put upon the
Duty of Prayer; for times of Affliction are
more properly times of Supplication and
Prayer; <hi>Call upon me,</hi> ſays God, <hi>in the day
of Trouble.</hi> Then God calls upon us to call
upon him; and then we are more apt to do
it, than at other times, as appears <hi>Iſa. 26. 16.
Lord, in Trouble have they viſited thee, and have
poured out a Prayer when thy chaſtening was
upon them.</hi> At other times Prayer came
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:172638:13"/>
from them but ſparingly and droppingly;
but <hi>when thy chaſtening was upon them, then
they poured out a Prayer;</hi> then they even pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
out their Hearts before the Lord.</p>
            <p>They meet with days of Trouble, that
they might more ſweetly taſte of Peace:
How ſweet is an hour's Reſt after many
toilſome and troubleſome Nights. That we
might reliſh Mercies the better, God doth
oftentimes ſawce them with troubleſome
Seaſons. O! How comfortable will a Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven
of Reſt be after troubleſome and dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous
Tempeſts at Sea, and ſo doubtleſs
Heaven will be Heaven indeed to him that
hath met with many Troubles and Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
here in this World. But yet here is our
Comfort here in this Life; Though the
days are never ſo evil, yet God is always
good, a ſtrong hold, to whom we may al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways
reſort, and knows all them that truſt
in him. And that is the next thing I ſhall
ſhew you, how then God is good, though
Men and the Times are never ſo bad.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>1ſt.</hi> God is good eſſentially, yea God is
Goodneſs it ſelf; and God muſt needs ceaſe
to be when he ceaſes to be good, he ceaſes
to be God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly.</hi> God is good efficiently; God is not
only good, but he doth good, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119. 68.
As the Sun doth not keep in his Beams to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:172638:13"/>
himſelf, but he ſpreads them abroad for the
good of the Univerſe: So <hi>God is good to all,</hi>
ſays the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal. 145. 9. and his tender
Mercies are over all his Works.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly.</hi> God is eminently good, and that to
his own People. God is univerſally good:
There is not any Creature in the World, but
he doth partake of the Goodneſs of God: In
ſome meaſure he makes his Sun to riſe upon
the Juſt and the Unjuſt, and he makes his
Rain to fall upon wicked Mens Fields, as
well as upon the Fields of the Righteous.
But God is in a more ſpecial manner good
to them that be good; <hi>Truly God is good to
Iſrael,</hi> ſays the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 72. 1. to all
that are of <hi>a clean Heart.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> But is he not good to all? Did
you not ſay he is good to all, may ſome ſay?
I, but not with the ſame Goodneſs, not with
ſaving Goodneſs; ſo he is good only to his
Elect, and ſo he is eternally good to them,
not only in this World, but alſo in the
World to come; God ceaſes to be good to
wicked Men in the World to come: <hi>Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
Son,</hi> ſays <hi>Abraham</hi> to <hi>Dives, thou hadſt
thy good things:</hi> I, thou hadſt them, but now
thou haſt them not. But now God is good
to his both in this World, and in the World
to come.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:172638:14"/>
Here in this World he is a Strong-hold to
them, when Enemies and Evils are abroad,
and a Houſe of Defence to which they may
always reſort in the time of Need and Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs:
God being a univerſal and perpetual
good God, is all in all in every Condition:
Bread is good to feed you, but it cannot
clothe you. Again, Clothes are good to
warm you, but they cannot feed you; but
God is good every way: <hi>My God,</hi> ſays the
Apoſtle, <hi>ſhall ſupply all your needs, according to
his riches in Glory by Chriſt Jeſus,</hi> Phil. 4. 19.
Not only ſome, but all your Needs, and he
doth all after the beſt ſort; he is a Father,
and the beſt Father; he is a Maſter, and
the beſt Maſter; he is a Friend, and the
beſt Friend; he is a Strong-hold, and the
beſt Strong-hold: and the Excellency of this
Strong-hold I ſhall endeavour to make out to
you thus.</p>
            <p>Firſt, He is a high Strong-hold; ſo high
indeed, that none can reach him that is
in this Strong-hold, or that hath God for his
Strong-hold to defend him; he ſhall be ſo
compaſt in with the Loving-kindneſs of God,
that nothing ſhall do him hurt: His <hi>Dwel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings
ſhall be on high,</hi> ſays the Prophet, <hi>his
Place of Defence ſhall be the Munitions of Rocks,
Bread ſhall be given, his Waters ſhall be ſure,
Iſa.</hi> 33. 16. See how God doth provide for
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:172638:14"/>
the Safety and Welfare of his, that <hi>he ſhall
dwell on high,</hi> out of Gun-ſhot, and ſo out of
Danger, for <hi>his place of defence ſhall be the
Munitions of Rocks,</hi> or Rock within Rock:
I, but Rocks, though they be good for fence,
yet they be naught for food; it was the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil
that would have Stones turned into
Bread. I, but rather than a Believer ſhall
ſtarve, he ſhall have Bread given: I, but
may he not periſh there for want of Water?
No, <hi>his Waters ſhall be ſure;</hi> ſo ſafe is he that
hath God for his Strong-hold.</p>
            <p>Secondly, God as he is a high Strong-hold,
ſo he is a nigh Strong-hold; ſome
may be cut off before they can get to their
Strong-hold; their Strong-hold may be ſo
far, that they may be never the better for
their Strong-hold: But what ſays the Pſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſt
concerning Almighty God, <hi>Pſal. 46. 1.
God is our Refuge and Strength, a very preſent
help in Trouble;</hi> not only a help, <hi>but a preſent
help, yea a very preſent help in time of Trouble.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, God is a capacious Strong-hold,
ready to receive all that fly unto him for
Defence in the name of Chriſt; and as
Chriſt ſays, <hi>He that comes unto me, I will in
no wiſe caſt out, John</hi> 6. 37. So thoſe that
come unto God by Chriſt, <hi>he will in no wiſe
keep out,</hi> for there is Room and Entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
enough to be found in him; ſome
Strong-holds are ſo narrow and ſtraight, that
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:172638:15"/>
if many fly unto them, they are fain to hang,
many of them, like Bees about the Hive's
Mouth, and cannot get in: But whoever
yet fled to God to hide him, and was not
received and defended by him?</p>
            <p>Fourthly, God is an inviſible Strong-hold,
ſuch a Strong-hold as all their Enemies are
not able to find out; and therefore all that
flee unto him, and get into him, muſt needs
be ſafe: We know when the Sodomites
would have offered Violence to <hi>Lot,</hi> and to
have pull'd him out of his Houſe, the Angels
ſmote them with Blindneſs that they could
not ſo much as find the Door, much leſs pull
him out of his Houſe: So when the Syrians
came with a great Army to carry away the
Prophet <hi>Eliſha,</hi> and had compaſſed the City
round, ſo that one would have thought there
could have been no eſcaping, yet then <hi>Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſha</hi>
had an inviſible Guard; and though his
Man could not ſee it at the firſt, yet after
the Prophet had pray'd to God to open his
Eyes, then he could ſee the Mountain full of
Horſes and Chariots of Fire round about his
Maſter.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, To name no more Properties and
Excellencies of this Strong-hold, God is an
invincible Strong-hold; other Strong-holds
are not able to hold out in the day of God's
Anger; the leaſt puff or puſh of God's Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſure
will thruſt them down. <hi>Nineveh</hi> that
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:172638:15"/>
ſtately City, that had Walls 100 foot high,
and beautified with 1300 Towers: All her
Strong-holds ſhall be like Fig-trees with the
firſt ripe Figs, which when they are ſhaken,
ſhall fall into the Mouth of the Eater: But
who can overthrow ſuch a Strong-hold as
God is, that is Almighty? <hi>Wo be to him that
ſtrives with his Maker.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Uſe</hi> I. If God be ſuch an excellent Strong-hold,
then ſee what a boſom you have here to
flee unto; that whatſoever evil days come,
yet if you have recourſe to him for your
Strong-hold, you may be ſure to be ſafe; and
take heed, I beſeech you, that you do not
ſet up your Reſt in any thing on this ſide
God. When it is a day of Trouble, as we
are threatned with ſuch a day at this time,
Counſel and Strength of Men and Horſes,
and Ships, cannot be a Strong-hold for us
without God. See what the Prophet ſays
in the ſecond Chapter of <hi>Iſaiah, Ceaſe from
Man, whoſe Breath is in his Noſtrils;</hi> and if
Man muſt be ceaſed from, much rather
muſt the things that Man hath made be cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed
from, as Ships and pleaſant Pictures, as
the Prophet inſtances in that Chapter. Now
there be theſe three things that may rap off
your Fingers from the Creature, or making
any thing your Strong-hold on this ſide
God.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:172638:16"/>
Now for this conſider,</p>
            <p>1. The Inutility or Unprofitableneſs of
all Creature-help in the day of Diſtreſs, in
the day of God's Anger; for <hi>Riches profit no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
in the day of God's Wrath,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solomon,
Prov.</hi> 11. 4. But they many times make the
Owner the more in danger, as the Gold
Ring hath made ſome to looſe the Finger:
<hi>And what ſhall it profit a Man,</hi> ſays our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour,
<hi>to gain the whole World, and to looſe his
own Soul.</hi> That were a Loſs above all other
Loſſes; thou haſt better loſe thy Wife, thy
Children, thy Houſe, thy Lands, nay, thy
Life it ſelf, than looſe thy Soul; and yet thus
many do to gain the World: But what
Profit when they come to take away thy
Soul? The things of this World have not ſo
much Worth in them as to deliver your
Souls from Death or Hell, or Damnation;
ſo that it coſt more to redeem one Soul than
all the World comes to: They have not ſo
much worth in them as to ſatisfy one of
your Debts; for no Man knows Love or
Hatred by all that is before him; they have
no power to pacify Conſcience in its Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs.</p>
            <p>The things of this World prove many
times lothing Torments to dying Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
and they are many times dying Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts
to living Chriſtians.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:172638:16"/>
2. The Mutability of the Creature:
There is a great deal of Mutability in the
Creature; you cannot ſay the Moon will
ſhine two days together with the ſame face;
ſo the things of the World are likened to the
Moon, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12. 1. The Woman, that is the
Church, is ſaid to have the <hi>Moon under her
Feet; i. e.</hi> All worldly things.</p>
            <p>Again, They are ſometimes likened to
the Wind, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. 2. ſays the Prophet there,
<hi>I ſaw the four Winds ſtriving upon the Sea.</hi>
And what were thoſe four Winds, but the
four Monarchies, ſtriving upon the Sea of
this World which ſhould be uppermoſt:
And ſo as the Moon doth not ſhine two
days together with the ſame face, no more
are you ſure the Wind will blow two hours
together in the ſame Quarter. The grateſt
Monarchies and Kingdoms are but ſo many
ſtormy and violent Winds; and will you
make that your Strong-hold that is ſo ſubject
to Alteration and Change? In a ſtormy day
will you go to a Shadow for your Refuge
or Shelter.</p>
            <p>3. Beſides all this, there is a Corruptibili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty
in all theſe things; ſo the Apoſtle ſpeaks
to this purpoſe, <hi>1 Pet.</hi> 1. 19. He calls there
Silver and Gold corruptible things, which
we are apt to account moſt durable: How
may all the Glory of the World, which we
are apt to account moſt ſhining and excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent,
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:172638:17"/>
be wink't into Blackneſs and Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs?
All the Glory of Man is but as the
Flower of Graſs: All <hi>Solomon</hi>'s Glory was
but that of the Lilly, of very ſhort Continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance;
the Flower may fade whilſt the
Stalk yet ſtandeth, and yet that within a
ſhort while will be caſt into the Oven: The
Flower may be nipt in the Bub; but if it be
let alone, it will fall of it ſelf, ſuch are Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture
Excellencies; and therefore I beſeech
you do not ſet up your Cities of Refuge on
this ſide God.</p>
            <p>And for your further comfort, conſider
how God knows ſuch as are in Trouble and
truſt in him, and have Dependance upon
him for Safety and Deliverance; if God's
People could be in Adverſity, and God not
know it, then their caſe would be ſad in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed;
but God knows what all your Ailes
and Troubles are, and will certainly deliver
you out of them all, if you depend upon him
and truſt in him.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Queſt.</hi> But are there not many that are
Believers, that are cut off in their Troubles
and Straits, as good <hi>Joſiah</hi> and others?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> There are ſeldom any that in the
height of their Dependance upon God, that
have acted Faith, and fully relied upon him
for Deliverance, that have been cut off: For
you muſt know that it is one thing to have
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:172638:17"/>
Faith, and another thing to act Faith; as it
is one thing to have a Sword, and another
thing to uſe it: Many a one may be cut off
for not uſing of his Sword; whereas if he
had uſed it, very like he might have eſcap'd;
and it is a Saying of the Pſalmiſt concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
the goldly Man, <hi>Pſal. 112. 7. He ſhall
not be afraid of any evil tydings:</hi> Why? <hi>His
Heart is fixed, truſting in the Lord.</hi> All the
while he acts his Faith on God, he hath no
cauſe to fear: So that this further informs us
that the Wicked ſhall never beat Believers
out of heart, for in the worſt times they
have a Strong-hold; a good God to run
unto, and ſo ſhall they be ſaved from all
their Enemies: When they are in the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt
danger, ſtill they have a God that takes
Cognizance of them, when it may be their
Friends and neer Relations will take no no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice
of them: <hi>Thou haſt known my Soul in Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities,</hi>
ſaith <hi>David, Pſal.</hi> 31. 7. If they
could be in Adverſities, and God not know
it, it would then be a ſad thing indeed; but
God knows whatſoever Adverſities you are
in, and will doubtleſs deliver his: I, but are
not many of them cut off by Death? I an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer;
God will be ſo good to them as to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver
them from Death or by Death, and
therefore the day of Death is better to them
than the day of their Birth; for when they
are born, then they come into Trouble, but
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:172638:18"/>
when they die then they come out of Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble;
and it is better to come out of Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,
than to come into Trouble. This is
the Comfort that they have that truſt in
God: God knows them, and knows how to
deliver them when they do not know how
to deliver themſelves; <hi>We know not what to
do,</hi> ſays <hi>Jehoſhaphat, 2 Chron.</hi> 20. 12. I, but
God knows what to do, and how to deliver
his, and to reſerve the Wicked for the day
of Wrath: For this Knowledg of God,
whereby he knoweth his, is not a bare
ſpeculative Knowledg, as he knoweth all
things, but as ſpecial Knowledg, as if he
knew none in the World beſide; as God ſaid
concerning his own People, <hi>Amos 3. 2. You
have I known of all the Families upon Earth;</hi>
and as God ſaid to <hi>Moſes, Thee have I known
by name:</hi> As if God knew none in the
World beſides after ſuch a ſort; and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
he hath his Marks whereby he diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhes
between his own People and others:
So <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 9. a Mark is ſet upon them that
mourn; as if he did, and would know them
from all the People on the Earth: So
<hi>2 Tim. 2. 19. The Lord knoweth who are his;</hi>
for it is indeed a Knowledg that doth im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply
Love and Affection to the Party that
he knows; and therefore, <hi>John</hi> 10. 10.
Chriſt is ſaid to know his Sheep. Why did
he not know the Goats, wicked and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:172638:18"/>
Men? Yes, doubtleſs he did; but he
did not know them with that Love and
Care, and Affection, as he did his Sheep;
and beſides, it is ſuch a Knowledg as doth
imply Approbation; ſo <hi>Pſal.</hi> 1. and the laſt
Verſe, <hi>The Lord knoweth the way of the Righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous.</hi>
Why, doth he not know the way of
the Unrighteous too? Yes, doubtleſs he
doth: Can they walk in ſuch a ſecret Path,
that God cannot find them out? Nay,
there is not a Way of their Feet, a Work
of their Hands, a Word of their Mouths,
or a Thought of their Hearts, but it is bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
known to God than to themſelves;
who is indeed the Father of Lights, and
will doubtleſs in his good time, bring
to light all the hidden Works of Dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs,
and Diſhoneſty and Cruelty, though
never ſo cunningly contrived, as he hath
done of late, to the Shame and Confuſion
of the Plotters: But as they have conceiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
Miſchief, let us conceive Praiſe, and let
us be often doing that Work upon Earth
which we ſhall be always doing in Heaven.
And to encourage you to the Duty, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider
that it is a greater matter to praiſe God
here upon Earth, in the midſt of Enemies,
than to praiſe God in Heaven, where all
Enemies are ſubdued, and all Happineſs
enjoyed, and none but ſuch as will help for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward
the Work, and none that will hinder
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:172638:19"/>
it, as here are too many here. And that
you may not be afraid of your Adverſaries,
or diſcouraged from truſting in God, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider,
though your Enemies carry it out for
the preſent with a great deal of Splendour
and Bravery, yet they are but Men, and
Men <hi>whoſe Breath is in their Noſtrils;</hi> and
when God takes it away, they die and can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not
withſtand God's ſtroak: Many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands
of them have been cut off in theſe Wars
already, that look'd upon themſelves as
brave Fellows.</p>
            <p>And beſides, they are on that ſide that
muſt fall: God hath ſaid it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that Antichriſt
and his Adherents muſt be deſtroyed, and
it ſhall certainly come to paſs; for hath the
Lord of Hoſts ſaid it, and ſhall he not do it,
whoſe Word is his Work? <hi>I will work ſays
God, and who ſhall let it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Beſides, as <hi>Abijah</hi> told <hi>Jeroboam, With you
are the Golden Calves;</hi> and ſo with our Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſaries
are graven Images, and they are
ſuch as have forſaken God, and defiled his
true Worſhip, and God hath forſaken them;
and let ſuch be our Enemies, as many, and
as much as they will, if we have but God
on our ſide, we ſhall do well enough.</p>
            <p>Again, Conſider, that you may not be
offended at their outward Bravery and
Splendour, how the triumphing of the
Wicked is but ſhort, but their end will be
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:172638:19"/>
that they ſhall periſh for ever; and on the
other ſide, though the Godly are afflicted,
yet they are not deſerted as the Ungodly
are; though they are caſt down, yet they
are not caſt off. <hi>Saul</hi> and <hi>David</hi> they were
both afflicted, and greatly diſtreſſed: <hi>Saul</hi>
in his Diſtreſs he runs to a Witch; <hi>O!</hi> ſays
<hi>Saul, I am ſorely diſtreſſed:</hi> Why ſo? Why
<hi>the Philiſtines make War againſt me:</hi> Why ſo
they had done formerly, and yet <hi>Saul</hi> did
then well enough. I, but ſays he, <hi>and God
is departed from me.</hi> I, there was the cauſe,
there lay the Core of all his Miſeries; for
this is like the dropping of the Eyes out of
the Head, the darkning of the Sun in the
Firmament, the departing of the Soul out
of the Body: Now <hi>David</hi> likewiſe, he was
greatly diſtreſſed for the City <hi>Ziglag,</hi> where
his Treaſure was that was burnt, and his
Wives they were carried away Captives,
and the People likewiſe they were ready to
ſtone him; ſo that his Treaſure was gone,
his Wives were gone, and the Hearts and
Affections of his People were gone off from
him. What doth he do now? Doth he go
to a Witch, or uſe any unlawful means, as
<hi>Saul</hi> did? No, he goes and encourages him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf
in the Lord his God, and you ſee how
bravely he comes off afterward.</p>
            <p>Hence we may ſee the Excellency of
Faith, and how Believers having ſuch a
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:172638:20"/>
Strong-hold, ſhall never be beat quite out
of heart, having ſo good a God to relie up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on;
for though their Enemies threaten and
rage never ſo much, yet Believers have di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers
Props to ſtay and uphold their Hearts
in days of Trouble, and to cauſe them not
to be diſmaid, but ſtill have cauſe to truſt in
God: As,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>1ſt.</hi> That the Devil and his Inſtruments,
wicked Men, they are all in the hand of
God, and they can do no more againſt them
than God gives them leave: It is true, God
ſometimes lets out a Link or two of the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil's
Chain, but ſtill he keeps the Chain in
his own hand, that he nor his cannot do
ſo much Miſchief as otherwiſe they
would.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly.</hi> When you are in any danger, you
muſt act Faith upon God; ſo the Prophet
reſolves to do, <hi>Pſalm 56. 3. What time I am
afraid, I will truſt in thee:</hi> Now that you
may be able to act Faith aright,</p>
            <p>1. You muſt labour to have a right
Knowledg of God, and of what God is;
for you cannot ſtay your Minds, and truſt
in him whom you do not know, and have
no Acquaintance with him: As one ſaid
ſometime to a Gentlemen that was walking
in <hi>Pauls, Pray lend me ten Pounds: Ten Pounds,</hi>
ſays the Gentleman, <hi>why I do not know you.</hi>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:172638:20"/>
Says the other, <hi>If you did, you would hardly
lend me ten Shillings.</hi> Some are better known
than truſted, but ſo is not God; but the
more you know him, the more apt you
will be to truſt in him, ſo <hi>Pſal.</hi> 9. 10. eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially
if it be an experimental Knowledg;
ſo <hi>Pſal. 22. 4. Our Fathers truſted in thee;
they truſted, and thou didſt deliver them:</hi> And
ſo if we, their Poſterity, truſt in God, God
will deliver us; <hi>They cried unto thee,</hi> ſaith
the Church, <hi>and were delivered; they truſted
in thee, and were not confounded:</hi> So doubt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
if we cry unto our Forefathers God, we
ſhall be delivered; if we truſt in him, and
have recourſe to him, we ſhall not be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>founded:
But confounded ſhall they be that
worſhip carved Images; as it is plain our
Adverſaries do. Well, but what is it that
we muſt know of God more eſpecially,
that we may be brought to truſt in him,
and depend upon him in a day of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſs?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>1ſt.</hi> God's Power, that he is able to
help and to defend his People, whatſoever
their Diſtreſſes and their Adverſaries are;
you muſt mightily work this upon your
Spirits, the Conſideration of the Power and
Greatneſs of God; therefore you have the
Greatneſs of God wonderfully ſet out in the
foregoing part of this Chapter, for God
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:172638:21"/>
will not imploy his Greatneſs againſt his
People, but for his People's good. As alſo
you are to take notice of the All-ſufficiency
of God, how he is able to ſave to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termoſt
all ſuch as put their truſt in him.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Abraham</hi> was as a poor Pilgrim,
and went from one Kingdom to another
People, to ſupport his Faith, God tells him,
<hi>I am God;</hi> All-ſufficient, walk before me,
and be thou perfect, and then he need not
be afraid: We can never ſtay our Minds,
and truſt in God ſo well as we ſhould, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
we relie upon God as a God All-ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient,
that is able to ſuccour us in every
Caſe and Condition. See what ſupported
the three Children, as they are commonly
called, againſt the Wrath of the great King,
<hi>Dan</hi> 3. 17. they ſtay their Minds greatly on
God; <hi>Our God,</hi> ſay they, <hi>is able to deliver
us:</hi> They did not fear the Wrath of the
great King, becauſe, with <hi>Moſes</hi> by an Eye
of Faith, they ſaw him that was inviſible;
they knew they had an invincible Strong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
to reſort unto, a good God that was
able to deliver them, how, and as he plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.
Now when you diſtruſt God's Power,
you do as it were tie up the hands of Om<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nipotency.
It is ſaid, <hi>Mark</hi> 6. 5. our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our
could do no mighty Works there, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
of their Unbelief: God doth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
wonderfully tutor his Children about
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:172638:21"/>
the Conſideration of his Power, as you may
obſerve in Scripture. When God promiſes
to appear in the way of ſaving and deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering
his People, he doth very much inſiſt
on this, what a powerful God he is, able to
do above what they are able to ask or
think, that ſo their Faith might be well
grounded upon a good foundation; ſee for
this a place or two, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 40. 9, 10. There
the Prophet ſpeaks by way of promiſe, that
<hi>the Lord God would come;</hi> i. e. to comfort
and relieve his People: He tells them he
<hi>would come with a ſtrong hand,</hi> and as it were
with an out-ſtretched arm, <hi>and his arm ſhall
rule for him:</hi> And he further inſiſts upon
this thing, and maketh it the great Theam
that he goeth upon. If you read the <hi>12th</hi>
Verſe of this Chapter, you ſhall find that
he had a ſtrong Hand indeed, and an Arm
ſtretched out, in that he was able to hold all
the Waters of the Sea, and to meaſure out
Heaven, which is, <hi>locus omnium Spacioſiſſimus,</hi>
with a Span, and that he was able to weigh
the Mountains in Scales, and the Hills in a
Balance; <hi>Behold,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>the Nations:</hi> By
Nations we are to underſtand great Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries
and Kingdoms; <hi>What are they but as
a drop of the Bucket, and as a ſmall duſt of
the Balance? Behold, he taketh up the Iſles as
a very little thing.</hi> As this Iſle, which we
call <hi>Great Britain,</hi> is a very little thing in
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:172638:22"/>
the hands of Almighty God; and when he
comes to the <hi>26th</hi> Verſe, there he calls up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
them to <hi>lift up their eyes, and to behold
him who hath created theſe things;</hi> ſo great
and ſo many, <hi>that bringeth out their hoſt by
number:</hi> He muſt needs be great himſelf,
that hath made ſo many, and ſuch great
things. And thus he goeth on to ſet forth
the Power and Greatneſs of God, to be a
ſupport to the Faith of his People: <hi>I have
wondred,</hi> ſaith a Godly and Learned Man,
<hi>that reading of Scripture in my younger years,
there ſhould be ſuch a ſuddain Digreſſion to the
Power of God, as there is; and now I ſee there
is a great deal of reaſon for it, to ſtrengthen
the Faith of his People, that they firmly believe
his Promiſes;</hi> as you may find, if you obſerve,
in many other places: So you have the
Power of God ſet forth in this Chapter.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly.</hi> If you would truſt in God, and
depend upon him in <hi>the day of trouble</hi> and
diſtreſs; as you muſt be very well princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pled
in the Power, ſo alſo in his Willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs
and Readineſs to ſuccour and to receive
you, and ſo to ſave you in the time of Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger
and Diſtreſs. Some have Power to do
good, but they have no heart to do it; you
muſt conſider, as there is an Ability in God
to do good, ſo there is a Propenſity to do
good: There is a very great Inclination in
God to help and to ſave his afflicted Ones.
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:172638:22"/>
obſerve, I pray, how the Scripture ſpeaks
to this, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 46. 1. It was at ſuch a time
when there was great Dread upon the face
of the Earth. The Prophet ſeems to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent
it ſo; as if the Earth ſhould totter
and be removed, and the Mountains car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried
into the midſt of the Sea, and the Wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters
roar and make a hideous noiſe, and all
things in a hurly-bury; yet there was no
cauſe for ſuch as truſt in God to fear, for
<hi>God is our Refuge and Strength,</hi> ſay they, <hi>our
Strong-hold, a very preſent Help in trouble.</hi>
He is not only a Help, but a preſent Help;
yea, <hi>a very preſent Help in trouble.</hi> The
great Willingneſs of God the Lord to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear
for them, appears in his Readineſs to
appear to them, if we do but call upon him
and cry to him; and he can do but little
that cannot cry for help. Now <hi>Pſalm</hi> the
86. 7. ſays the Prophet, <hi>In the day of my
Trouble I will call upon thee; for thou wilt
anſwer me.</hi> The God of a true Believer is
not like the God of <hi>Baal</hi>'s Prieſts, upon
whom they called from Morning even till
Noon, ſaying, <hi>O Baal, hear us:</hi> But there
was no Voice, nor any that anſwered; no
more there would have been if they had
prayed never ſo long; if he had prayed
till Doomſday, it had been all one: But
no ſooner doth the true Prophet pray, but
preſently Fire comes down from Heaven,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:172638:23"/>
and conſumes the Sacrifice, for the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion
of the Churches Adverſaries. And
how doth the Prophet promiſe to himſelf,
in the fore-named place, how God would
hear him? Which he could not have done,
but that he was aſſured of his Willingneſs
ſo to do; for he doth not ſay, <hi>the Lord
can hear me,</hi> but <hi>the Lord will hear me:</hi>
And he ſaith nothing but what he hath a
Promiſe for upon the Performance of the
foreſaid Duty. Nay further, to ſhew his
Readineſs and Willingneſs to hear and help,
it is ſaid in one place, <hi>That before they call,
I will anſwer; and while they are yet ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing,
I will hear.</hi> So no ſooner did the Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per
ſay, <hi>Matth. 8. 2. Lord, if thou wilt thou
canſt make me clean;</hi> but preſently Chriſt
replies, <hi>I will, be thou clean;</hi> as if he eccho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
back the ſame words; and immediately
ſays the Text, <hi>his Leproſie was cleanſed:</hi>
And that there is a great deal of Readineſs
and Willingneſs in God to help, you muſt
conſider how God doth take ſpecial no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice
of the Trouble and Afflictions that
his People lie under, and how he is apt to
lay it to heart; for in all their Afflictions
he is afflicted; <hi>I have ſurely ſeen,</hi> ſays God,
<hi>the Affliction of my People, and have heard
their Cry,</hi> Exod. 3. 7. It is not with him,
as it is with ſome that paſs by ſuch as are
in Miſery, and take little or no notice of
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:172638:23"/>
their Trouble, as the Prieſt and Levite that
ſaw the Man wounded and half dead, and
there let him lye for all them. But if God's
People are never ſo little wronged, he is
preſently concerned; if they are reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,
they are reproached in his ſight: He
takes it as done to himſelf; <hi>He that touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
you,</hi> ſays God, <hi>toucheth the Apple of mine
Eye,</hi> Zach. 2. 8. So he that perſecuteth
the People of God, it is as if he did per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecute
Chriſt himſelf, <hi>Acts</hi> 9. 5. And all
the Rage that they expreſs againſt the
People of God, it is ſet down as done
againſt God himſelf; <hi>I know,</hi> ſays God,
<hi>thy abode, and thy going out and thy coming
in, and thy Rage againſt me:</hi> It is all down
in black and white, what the World doth
for, or againſt his Children.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>3dly.</hi> God doth not only look on his
Peoples Affliction, but it is the lovingeſt
Look, and with as much Compaſſion, as
poſſible may be imagined; as you may
ſee <hi>Pſal. 103. 13. Like as a Father pitieth
his Children, the like Pity doth the Lord
ſhew to thoſe that are his:</hi> His Look ſhews
his Love, as you may ſee <hi>Exod.</hi> 2. 23, 25.
It pierces his very Heart, to hear their
Sighs, and to ſee their Miſeries: So their
Sorrows came up when his People were
afflicted in <hi>Egypt;</hi> it is ſaid in the place
named before, that the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:172638:24"/>
ſighed by reaſon of their hard Bondage,
and God heard their groaning, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membred
his Covenant, which was to be
a Friend to their Friends, and an Enemy
to their Enemies; and God looked upon
the Children of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> How, I pray, did
he look? Why he had reſpect unto them,
though their Enemies did nothing regard
them, no not ſo much as a Man would
regard his Beaſt. Again, God declares his
Willingneſs in regard he commands his
People to come to him, and call upon him
in <hi>the day of trouble;</hi> and tells them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al,
that unleſs they do thus, they are like
to go without his help: For thus he tells
his own People, <hi>Ezek. 36. 37. I will for
this be enquired of by the houſe of</hi> Iſrael <hi>to
do it for them;</hi> for God would not have
his People to ſeek his face in vain. And
in another place God complains, <hi>Thou
haſt not called upon me, O Jacob,</hi> Iſa. 43. 21.
You know if a Man be not willing to help,
if he have power, yet if he have no mind
to help, a poor Creature cannot with any
face go to him: but God is ſo far from
diſcouraging any from coming to him,
that he invites them to come, and aſſures
them that if they come, <hi>he will in no wiſe
caſt them out:</hi> And indeed commands them
for to come, and commands Silence in
Heaven till his People tell their Tale;
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:172638:24"/>
and doth bow down his Ear to hear
what his People can ſay for themſelves,
and as a Parent to his Child, <hi>O! what
wouldſt thou have?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If God were not willing to help, he
would ſay, as he did to the Wicked, <hi>Pſal.
50. 16. What haſt thou to do?</hi> With my
Word you ſhall not take my Name in
your Mouth; or if you do, it ſhall be in
vain; if you make many Prayers, I will
not hear you. But he readily grants the
Requeſts of his People: <hi>O!</hi> ſays the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet,
<hi>he will be very gracious to thee at the
Voice of thy Cry; when he ſhall hear it, he
will anſwer thee,</hi> Iſa. 30. 19. So no ſooner
did <hi>Daniel,</hi> 10. 12. ſet himſelf to ſeek
God, but his words were heard: So when
we ſeek God by Prayer, as we ought to
do, God will ſend Mercy poſt haſte to his
People: Now would he doth us, if he were
not willing to help them, and to be a Srong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold
to them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>4thly.</hi> If you would truſt in God aright,
you muſt clear up your Intereſt in God;
That this God that is thus able and
willing to help and defend, is your God;
That you can claim an Intereſt in him,
and that you are his; That he knows
you to be his Friends and Acquaintance
by your often coming to him, and that
you know him to be your Father in
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:172638:25"/>
Chriſt: You will never come to cloſe
with God with any Confidence, when
you come to have need of him, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs
you can clear up your Intereſt in
him; otherwiſe here will be apt to come
in diſmaying Thoughts. I know indeed
that God can ſave me, and can defend
me; but can I ſay, upon good grounds,
as the Prophet did, <hi>I am thine, ſave me?</hi>
I have ſo often ſinn'd againſt him, that I
have great cauſe to queſtion whether this
God be my God; this will turn back the
Milk in the Breaſt of the Promiſe: The
Scripture doth wonderfully declare this,
as in the <hi>Pſalm 48. ult. This God is
our God:</hi> as if no others had any intereſt
in him: And ſo <hi>Pſal. 67. 6. God even our
own God ſhall bleſs us;</hi> and ſo <hi>Iſa. 25. 9.
Lo, this God is our God, we have waited for
him, and he will ſave us; we will rejoice,
and be glad in his Salvation.</hi> This was
that ſtayed their Minds up, and kept them
from deſpair; and ſo this was that kept
up the Spirits of thoſe three Worthies,
<hi>Dan.</hi> 3. 17. They firſt lay claim to God,
and clear up their Intereſt in him, and
then they conclude, <hi>he will ſave us out of
thine hand, O King;</hi> and ſo he did. So
when there was ſuch a mighty Army and
great Multitude came out againſt <hi>Jehoſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phat,</hi>
and againſt his People, what do they
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:172638:25"/>
then but clear up their Intereſt in God?
<hi>Art not thou our God,</hi> ſay they, <hi>2 Chron.
20. ver.</hi> 7. and then <hi>ver. 12. O our God,
wilt thou not judge them.</hi> Which words are
to be reſolved affirmatively; <hi>Thou being,
our God, wilt certainly judge them, and avenge
our cauſe;</hi> and ſo he did. So that when
you have cleared up your Intereſt in God
in <hi>a day of trouble,</hi> then ſet Faith on work
without Fear; labour fully to relie upon
God, and to truſt in him: Be the Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles
as many, and as great as may be, yet
believe that you have a God that is able
to defend you, and to deliver you out of
them all. Know this, that it is the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonableſt
thing in the World, after thou
haſt cleared up that thou haſt a real In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt
in God, to doubt that he will deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
thee, or take thy part, or be graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous
to thee, when thou haſt made out
to thy ſelf that thou haſt an Intereſt in
him. Would it not be an unnatural thing
for a Child that hath had Experience of
his Father's Kindneſs to him, and ready
to relieve any that hath come to him
when they have been in diſtreſs, now for
this Child to doubt of his Help? and to
ſay, If I were in want, would my Father
relieve? If I were purſued by an Enemy
to my Father's Door, would he receive
me? Were I in the Water ready to be
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:172638:26"/>
drowned, would he help me out? Or
were I fallen in the Fire, would my Father
pluck me out? Surely if thou canſt find
upon good grounds, that God is thy God,
and thy Father in Chriſt, and taken poſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion
of thy Soul, would it be a ſeemly
thing for thee to reaſon thus? If I were
poor or deſpiſed in the World, would God
own me or know me? Yes, if you own
and acknowledg him to be your God
Doth not the Text ſay, that <hi>he knows them
that truſt in him?</hi> be they never ſo poor
or mean in the World. We read of Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers
in <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 37. how <hi>they wandred
about in ſheeps-skins and goat-skins, being de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitute,
afflicted, tormented;</hi> and yet it is ſaid
in the ſame Chapter, at <hi>ver. 16. God is
not aſhamed to be called their God:</hi> For they
are the Poor chiefly that put their Truſt
in God, that have nothing elſe to truſt
too; ſo <hi>Zeph. 3. 12. I will leave in the midſt
of thee a poor People, and they ſhall truſt in
the name of the Lord.</hi> And the <hi>Widow be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
deſolate,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>1 Tim. 5. 5.
truſteth in God:</hi> Before, whilſt ſhe had a
Husband, ſhe relyed on him; but being
deſolate, and having none to regard her,
or to provide for her, ſhe truſts in God,
and God knows all them that truſt in him,
be they never ſo poor; it is not Poverty
ſhall part God and a Believer: As it is
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:172638:26"/>
ſtoried of Mr. <hi>Fox,</hi> that wrote the Book
of Martyrs; being asked, Whether he did
not know ſuch as were but poor in Eſtate
and mean in Perſon, but godly in their
Lives and Converſations? <hi>O!</hi> ſays he, <hi>I
forgot Lords and Ladies to remember ſuch:</hi>
So God, though he be High, yet hath he
reſpect to the Lowly; the moſt High hath
moſt reſpect to the moſt Low, and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>looks
the Proud and Stately; and though
he ſits upon a moſt high Throne, yet doth
he look with a Look of Favour and Love
to him that is poor, <hi>and of a contrite Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi>
and that trembles at, and truſts in
his Word; and therefore away theſe
Doubts: If I be poor, will God own me:
Or if I be in ſtreights, will he relieve
me? Or if I be in danger, will he be a
Strong-hold, or a Place of Refuge to me?
Away with all theſe If's and Doubts;
ſet thy Faith on work, and fall flatly to
believing. Thus did the Father of the
Faithful, ſetting Faith on work without
Fear, and ſtaying himſelf on God, as ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king
a Promiſe, and afterwards as break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
a Promiſe; who firſt upon a Promiſe
gave him a Son, and afterwards bids him
<hi>go and offer up thy Son,</hi> Gen. 22. kill him,
ſlay him with thine own hands. Now if
you look into <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. there is made out
to <hi>Abraham</hi> the Intereſt that he had in
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:172638:27"/>
God; and God tells him there, <hi>I am thy
ſhield, and thy exceeding great reward.</hi> Well,
now when God had made out to <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham</hi>
his Intereſt, he puts him upon
Streights and great Trials; and this hot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt
Trial of all, the offering up of his
only Son by <hi>Sarah,</hi> his dearly beloved Wife:
Well, thought <hi>Abraham,</hi> if I muſt do it,
ſurely God will do me good by it, as his
Grandſon <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaid in another caſe.
What did <hi>Abraham,</hi> when his Intereſt
that he had in God was made out to
him, but falls to flat believing? Says the
Apoſtle, <hi>Rom. 4. 20. He ſtaggered not.</hi> For
he that was able to raiſe his Son from
the dead, as well as he could make the
barren Womb of <hi>Sarah</hi> for to bear, and
to bring him forth; O! is a Conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion
of great worth. If you can once
find upon Scripture-grounds, that God is
your God, (but take heed, I pray you of
falſe and deceitful grounds;) you may be
ſure God will ſtay up your Hearts in any
diſtreſs. If you are his, and rely wholly
upon him, you have both God's hand
and ſeal to do you good. Conſider <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi>
how in his Troubles he fell to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieving;
and you know what great Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles
he paſſed through, greater than ever
<hi>Saul</hi> had when he had his Intereſt clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
up in God: And whatſoever his Trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:172638:27"/>
were, he ſet Faith on work; he bids
Faith fall on, and fear not: Though
Troubles were on this ſide, and on that
ſide, nay round about, yet ſee how blunt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
he falls on, <hi>Pſal. 25. 2. O, my God, I
truſt in thee, I truſt in thee:</hi> I know I have
many and mighty Adverſaries, but I rely
only upon thee, do thou conſider which
way thou wilt rid me of them, and bring
me out of my Trouble. He did not ſay,
Will the Lord, or will God help me? and
will the Lord be found of me? He did
not ſtagger thus, but he bids Faith fall on;
<hi>O, my God, I truſt in thee, I will not fear
what Man can do unto me.</hi> Beloved, it is
an excellent thing, not, when Troubles
come, to ſtand as a People amazed; but
let Faith lay hold on God as a God Al-ſufficient.
Tell God with Reverence, you
will commit all to him: As a Duke, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
about to make War with a Biſhop,
before he engaged in the War he ſends out
a Spy to take notice what the Biſhop ſaid,
and how he behaved himſelf. Who re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turning,
the Duke askt him, What the
Biſhop was doing, and how he behaved
himſelf? Says he, the Biſhop ſeems to be
very careleſs; he ſays, He will preach the
Word, and ſeed his Flock, and <hi>totius belli
molem deo Ommittet.</hi> I, ſays the Duke,
ſays he ſo, <hi>Tunc ei bellum inferat Diabolus
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:172638:28"/>
non Ego;</hi> Then let the Devil make War
with him for me. Thus Faith will di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect
all your Affairs to God; and having
ſo done, hence will ariſe abundance of
ſweet Peace and Quiet in your Minds.
The reaſon of all the Diſquiet that is at
any time on the Spirits of God's People,
eſpecially in days of Trouble, is becauſe
they cannot truſt God, and ſtay their
Minds on him: They cannot believe,
and that makes the poor Soul to toſs and
tumble up and down; they are afflicted
with this fear and that fear. What ſays
the Prophet, <hi>Iſa. 7. 9. If you will not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve,
ſurely you ſhall not be eſtabliſhed:</hi> God
will be found to be faithful if you would
truſt in him, and rely upon him: Faith,
it will ſet you upon the Rock that is
higher than your ſelves, higher than any,
nay than all your Adverſaries; ſo that
when the Winds blow, and the Storms
beat, and the Waves roar and rage againſt
a Rock that ſtands firm and ſtedfaſt in
the midſt of the Sea, againſt which, as
Adverſaries, the Waves foam and ſpit, and
ſplit themſelves with rage; yet he on
ſuch a Rock ſits and laughs, and remain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
ſafe. A notable Inſtance we have in
<hi>Matth.</hi> 14. of the Condition of ſuch a one
as doth believe. Our Saviour would there
teach us by Example what truſting in
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:172638:28"/>
God will do, and how when our Faith
fails, then we ſhall fail our ſelves. In that
Chapter you have how there, they were
at Sea: Now Chriſt that could truſt his
Father, and ſtay his Mind upon God, he
needs no Ship as the Diſciples did, to keep
him from drowning; he could walk on
the Sea, as you may ſee he did <hi>ver.</hi> 25.
yet doubtleſs then the Waves did toſs about
Chriſt, ſo that he muſt needs be, in appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,
in a dangerous Condition: Yet Chriſt
he could ſtay his Mind on God, his Faith
kept him up that he could not ſink: But
now they that were in the Ship not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
who this was, cried out: <hi>Why,</hi> ſays
Chriſt to them, <hi>it is I, be not afraid.</hi> He
ſet out before them a moſt glorious Inſtance
of what Faith could do, in his walking up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
the Water. Now <hi>Peter</hi> that had ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
of this Grace wrought in him by the
Power of God, ſays he to Chriſt, <hi>Lord, if
it be thou, bid me to come to thee on the Water:
Why come,</hi> ſays Chriſt; ſo <hi>Peter</hi> came down,
and walked on the Water to go to Chriſt,
but at length he began to ſink. Mark, ſo
long as his Faith kept firm, his Feet kept
firm, and he was able to walk upon the
Water; the Water was as a Floor under
him; but now mark, his Truſt began to
fail on a ſudden, as Faith will many times
ebb and flow in a moment. Now as his
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:172638:29"/>
Faith began to ſink, his Feet began to ſink,
for he had ſome Faith, though it was but lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle:
Mark therefore how clearly this is
made out; for when he ſaw the Wind boi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterous,
<hi>ver.</hi> 30. Why did he not ſee it ſo
when he was in the Ship? Yes, doubtleſs
it was, as you may find <hi>ver.</hi> 24. but then he
had a believing ſight of Chriſt; but now
his Faith that began to grow weak, and to
ſink within him; but immediately Chriſt
put forth his Hand, and caught him, and
ſaid, <hi>O, thou of little faith, wherefore didſt
thou doubt?</hi> So ready is Chriſt to ſuccour
ſuch as have any, though but a weak Faith:
as if Chriſt had ſaid, I confeſs thou wert in
a place of great danger, the Sea wide, and
the Winds high, and the Waves boiſterous,
but yet if thou couldeſt have believed, thou
ſhouldeſt have done well enough; the Lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleneſs
of thy Faith, it was that that made
thee ſink: So that you ſee how ready God
is to relieve Faith, though it be but little;
for which I may give you many Reaſons, I
will name but two.</p>
            <p>Firſt, Becauſe this is a Grace that is ſo
much deſpiſed by the Men of the World,
and are apt to upbraid thoſe that place their
Truſt in God, as we have an Inſtance of
this in Chriſt himſelf; <hi>O,</hi> ſay they, <hi>Mat.
27. 43. he truſted in God, let him deliver him
now if he will have him:</hi> And ſo the Apoſtle
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:172638:29"/>
               <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeaks of himſelf, and others the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants
of God, <hi>1 Tim. 4. 10. For therefore we
both labour and ſuffer reproach, becauſe we truſt
in the living God;</hi> ſo likewiſe <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14. 6.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Becauſe by truſting in God,
the Poor commit themſelves to God when
they have nothing elſe to truſt to, as the
Widow being deſolate, ſays the Apoſtle,
<hi>1 Tim. 5. 5. truſts in God;</hi> and ſo <hi>Zeph. 3. 12.
I will leave in the midſt of thee a poor People,
and they ſhall truſt in the Name of the Lord:</hi>
Though they be poor, and never ſo mean,
yet if they truſt in God, he will never leave
them nor forſake them.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
